Guide to the Arthur A. Allen papers,1899-1968,
Allen, Arthur A. papers,1899-1968,
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Arthur A. Allen papers, 1899-1968, 1899-1964(bulk).
21-18-1255
Arthur A.(Arthur Augustus), Allen 1885-1964.
65.8 cubic ft.
Audio Recordings, Correspondence, Movie Film, Photographs, Publications, Research Materials
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Papers consist largely of Allen's professional correspondence and his work in the field of ornithology.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Arthur Augustus Allen graduated from Cornell University in 1907, received an M.A. in 1908 and a Ph.D. in 1911. He served as professor of ornithology at Cornell University from 1916 until his appointment as professor emeritus in 1953. In 1919, he taught the first wildlife conservation course in the United States. Allen wrote for Magazines and journals, and authored several books, including The Book of Bird Life, 1930; American Bird Biographies, 1934; Ornithological Laboratory Notebook, 1936, 1941; The Golden Plover and Other Birds, 1939; as well as phonograph records and book sets from 1940 to 1964.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Papers consist largely of professional correspondence, his notes as a student, course and departmental files, field notes and bird observation charts, manuscripts of his articles and books, unpublished papers and reprints by other ornithologists, tape recordings, phonograph records and recordmasters, slides, glass plate negatives, half-tone printing blocks, lantern slides, photographs and films; topics documented include bird-banding, bird identification, slide and record sales, advice to prospective and former graduate students, lecture engagements and tours, professional meetings of organizations such as the American Ornithologists' Union and the American Game Association (American Game Protective and Propogation Association), his expeditions to Panama, Hudson Bay, Labrador, Mexico and Alaska, wildlife conservation and game management, his friendship with Louis Agassiz Fuertes, his fifteen-year study of the raising of the ruffed grouse in captivity, his study of the ivory-billed woodpecker, and the acquisition, design, building, and operation of the Laboratory of Ornithology, Cornell University. Also included are personal papers, primarily correspondence with Elsa Guerdrum, whom he married in 1913, as well as correspondence with other family members, and genealogical tables of the Allen family.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Allen, Arthur A.1885-1964.; Allen family.; Allen, Elsa Guerdrum.; Fuertes, Louis Agassiz, 1874-1927.; American Game Protective and Propogation Association.; American Ornithologists' Union.; Cornell University--Curricula.; Cornell University--Students.; Cornell University.Laboratory of Ornithology.
Subjects:
Bird banding.; Bird photography.; Bird refuges.; Birds--Societies, etc.; Ornithology--Study and teaching.; Ruffed grouse.; Wildlife conservation.; Woodpeckers.; Ornithologists.
Places:
Alaska.; Hudson Bay (Canada).; Labrador.; Mexico.; Panama.
Form and Genre Terms:
Genealogies.; Wet collodion negatives.; Lantern slides.; Photographs.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
Access Restrictions:
Restricted to permission of Prudence Allen Bentley.
A copy of the printed guide is available by clicking here. (Searchable PDF)
The paper guide contains a more detailed listing of the names found in the correspondence in the collection. Not all the material in the collection is covered by the PDF guide.
Page numbers below refer to the page number of the entire document and are not the number printed on the original page.
Introduction, collection arrangement, box overview, directions, abbreviations used. - Pages 1-31. Note that Tape recordings are now in Boxes 148-160 and glass plate negatives are in Box 161.
List of some glass plate negatives - Pages 32 - 47
Alphabetical subject index - Pages 48 - 665. Use this to search for individual names not found in the online guide.
RELATED MATERIALS
Described in DOCUMENTATION NEWSLETTER, Vol. III, No. 2, Fall 1977.
See also the Elsa Guerdrum Allen papers, #21-18-1362, http://resolver.library.cornell.edu/cgi-bin/EADresolver?id=RMA01362.
SERIES LIST
Series I. Biographical Materials
Personal Documents
Boxes 1-3, 183 and map case
Allen Family Genealogy
Box 4 and map case
Personal Photographs
Box 4
Personal Papers - Children
Box 4
Personal Correspondence
Boxes 5-13
Business Correspondence
Boxes 14-27, 181
Series II. Professional Correspondence
General
Boxes 28-99
Daily File
Boxes 100-104
Professional Engagements
Boxes 105-115
Louis Agassiz Fuertes
Box 116
Grouse
Boxes 117-119
Series III. Journals
Field Notes
Box 120
Study and Expedition Journals
Box 120
Series IV. Organizations
Box 120
Series V. Wildlife Refuge Creation
Boxes 121-122
Series VI. Manuscripts and Reprints by Arthur Allen
By Title: A-G
Box 122
By Title: H-N
Box 123
By Title: O-Z
Box 124
Miscellaneous
Box 124
Series VII. Teaching and Cornell University
Course Outlines and Lecture Notes
Boxes 124-127
College of Agriculture Related Records
Boxex 127, 128, 167-173
Series VIII. Radio Talks
Series IX. Papers and Reprints by Others
By Last Name of Author: A-D
Box 129
By Last Name of Author: D-H
Box 130
By Last Name of Author: H, J-P
Box 131
By Last Name of Author: P, S-U, W
Box 132
Series X. Photographic and Motion Picture Materials
Photographs and Some Sketches
Boxes 133-139, 181, 182 and map case
Motion Picture Film Clips
Boxes 140-154
Videos
VHS and DVD
Glass Plate Negatives
Boxes 155, 156, 161, 166, 176-179
Glass Slides
Boxes 162, 165
Series XI. Phonographic Records and Sound Recordings
Phonographic Record Booklets
Box 157
Phonograph Records
Boxes 160, 174
Tape Recordings
Boxes 158-160
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Biographical Materials
  - Personal Documents
    - Biographies and Biographical Material (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Professional career, tax and insurance documents, 1910-1952 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Legal documents and tax forms, 1913-1968 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Vertebrate Zoology notebook, 1904-1905 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Biology notebook, 1904-1905 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Botany notebook, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Physics 2C and 2D notebook - 2 notebooks, 1904 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Physics 2C and 2D, Second Semester notebook - 2 notebooks, 1905-1908 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Geology notebook and Dynamic, Structural and Physio-graphic Geology: Syllabus for Lectures by Ralph S. Tarr, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Chemistry notebook, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Histology, Photography, and Zoology notebooks, 1905-1906 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - English and Economic Entomology, 1905-1908 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Mycology notebook, 1905-1906 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Ornithology - bird sightings and nest locations, 1905-1906 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Ecology notebook, 1906 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Organography notebook, 1906 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Notes on plant species (Botany), undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Political Economy notebook, 1906-1907 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Entomology, 1907 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Elementary Zoology - Anatomy Drawings notebook, 1906-1907 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Farm Botany, 1906-1907 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Psychology, 1907 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Field notebooks of Ithaca waterways and water organisms, 1908 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - List of Bird Skins in the Cornell University Collection, 1908 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Neurology and Vertebrate Zoology, 1907 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Mammalogy and other miscellaneous notes, 1908 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - "Habits of the Short-tailed Shrew Blarina Brevicauda" - review of an article, 1909 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - "The Bats of this Region" paper, 1908 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Neurology and Vertebrate Zoology: Advanced Taxonomy, 1908-1909 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Entomology - Elementary Morphology, 1908 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - "The Migration of Animals" - outline, 1909 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Field notes: Growth of vegetation and Bird's nests; Chautaugua, 1910 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Outline for the proposed Ecological Study of Renwick Marsh, 1909 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Vertebrate Embryology notebook, 1910 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Morphology of Invertebrates notebook, 1910 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Zoology I: Invertebrates, 1910-1911 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Vertebrate I, 1911 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Vertebrate Zoology IV and the Fish of Cayuga Basin notes, 1911 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Limnology, 1911 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Zoology IV, Bibliography of bird related materials; paper on Organic Selection; bord observation notebook, 1911 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Bird related materials, 1914-1918 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Bird illustrations and notes (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Professional development materials - publications, contacts and references (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Clippings of bird illustrations and miscellaneous bird related (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Agassiz Club and other items related to Louis Agassiz, 1908-1911 (Box 2, Folder 21)
      Mainly Photocopies
    - Ballads sung a the Cornell Alumni Club Dinner - program, 1909 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Awards and Certificates, 1909-1955 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - "History of the Class of 1903" scroll and medal from the Sons of the American Revolution, 1903, undated (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Award: President of The Wildlife Society, 1938-1939 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Award from the Detroit Audubon Society, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Dinner for Arthur Allen: RSVP and attendee lists, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Photocopies of newspaper clippings regarding Allen, 1916-1934 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Photocopies of newspaper clippings regarding Allen, 1935-1940 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Photocopies of newspaper clippings regarding Allen, 1948-1967 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Slides of Arthur and Elsa Allen at a celebration at the Lab, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - 1908 Class Reunion Materials, 1958 and 1963 (Box 2, Folder 32)
      Includes photograph
    - Scrap book given by current and former students, 1950 (Box 2, Volume 1)
      Includes letters and photographs
    - Bibliographic and note cards (Box 3)
    - Field notes, c. 1884-1909 (Box 183)
      This notebook has been treated by conservation for mold damage
    - Diplomas and Certificates, 1907-1941 (Mapcase-folder 1a and 1b)
  - Allen Family Genealogy
    - Letters to other family members - mainly the Allen children, 1927-1967 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Allen Family Genealogy (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Allen Family Genealogy: Family documents (Box 4, Folder 3)
      Mainly photostats
    - Allen Family Genealogy: Photographs (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Allen Family Genealogy (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Allen Family Genealogy (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Letters to other family members: Anna Allen, 1912-1916, undated (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Anna Allen's Zoology and Ornithology notebooks, 1905-1906 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Letters to other Family Members: to Mother from Carrie (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Allen Family Genealogy (Mapcase-folder 2)
  - Personal Photographs
    - Allen Family Genealogy: Photographs (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Photo Album of Allen's time at Cornell, 1906-1908 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Photographs of Arthur Allen, undated (Box 4, Folder 12-13)
    - Photo album of the "Contingent", 1909 (Box 4, Folder 14)
      Where Elsa Guerdrum Allen met Arthur
    - Photo Album, 1913-undated (Box 4, Folder 15)
      Allen Family
    - Photo Album, undated (Box 4, Folder 16)
      Camping trips
    - Saga of the Highlands of Ontario, 1903-1963 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Photographs Allen Family (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Photographs Miscellaneous (Box 4, Folder 19-20)
    - Photographs of Glen Allen (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Photographs of Connie Allen (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Photographs of Phoebe Allen (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - Photographs of David Allen (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - Photographs of Prudence Allen (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - Photographs of Allen children and grandchildren (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Personal Papers - Children
    - Glen Allen's examination books from Cornell University (Box 4, Folder 27-29)
    - Keats-Shelley Journal: "The Fall of the Endymion: A Study in Keats’s Intellectual Growth" by Glen Allen, 1957 (Box 4, Folder 30)
    - Glen Allen's Student Materials, 1930-1943 (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - Connie Allen Materials, 1922-1965 (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - Phoebe and Glen Allen - Government I: Scrap Book, 1938 (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - David Allen Materials, 1944-1949 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Personal Correspondence
    - June 16, 1909 - December 30, 1909, 1909 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - December 30, 1909 - July 11, 1910, 1909-1910 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - July 12/13, 1910 - August 11, 1910, 1910 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - August 12, 1910 - September 30, 1910, 1910 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - October 7, 1910 - December 30, 1910, 1910 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - February 3, 1911 - June 17, 1911, 1911 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - June 15, 1911 - August 1, 1911, 1911 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - August 15, 1911 - December 17, 1911, 1911-1912 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - January 6, 1912 - March 18, 1912, 1912 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - March 26, 1912 - June 22, 1912, 1912 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - June 25, 1912 - July 15, 1912, 1912 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - August 3, 1912 - August 13, 1912, 1912 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - August 14, 1912 - August 19, 1912, 1912 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - August 19, 1912 - August 28, 1912, 1912 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - August 25, 1912 - August 31, 1912, 1912 (Box 6, Folder 1)
      Restricted
    - September 1, 1912 - September 5, 1912, 1912 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - September 5, 1912 - September 18, 1912, 1912 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - September 19, 1912 - October 1, 1912, 1912 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - October 6, 1912 - October 28, 1912, 1912 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - November 5, 1912 - November 23, 1912, 1912 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - November 24, 1912 - January 4, 1913, 1912-1913 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - January 7, 1913 - 1913 (undated), 1913 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - February 9, 1913 - March 15, 1913, 1913 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - March 17, 1913 - April 18, 1913, 1913 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - April 20, 1913 - June 20, 1913, 1913 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - June 25, 1913 - July 25, 1913, 1913 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - July 26, 1913 - August 4, 1913, 1913 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - August 5, 1913 - August 20, 1913, 1913 (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - August 23, 1913 - 1913 (undated), 1913 (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - January 13, 1914 - May 23, 1914, 1914 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - May 24, 1914 - June 2, 1914, 1914 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - June 2, 1914 - 1914 (undated), 1914 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - January 3, 1915 - June 21, 1915, 1915 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - June 23, 1915 - 1915 (undated), 1915 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - January 2, 1916 - May 19, 1916, 1916 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - May 28, 1916 - September 18, 1916, 1916 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - September 21, 1916 - December 28, 1916, 1916 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - 1916 and 1917 (undated) - December 30, 1917, 1916- (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - May 3, 1918 - May 17, 1918, 1918 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - May 22, 1918 - 1919 (undated), 1918-1919 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - September 2, 1919 - January 22, 1920, 1919-1920 (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - February 13, 1920 - January 16, 1921, 1920-1921 (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - February 3, 1921 - July 1, 1921, 1921 (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - July 22, 1921 - November 8, 1921, 1921 (Box 7, Folder 15)
    - November 10, 1921 - 1922 (undated), 1921-1922 (Box 7, Folder 16)
    - January 22, 1922 - May 6, 1922, 1922 (Box 7, Folder 17)
    - May 7, 1922 - September 20, 1922, 1922 (Box 7, Folder 18)
    - September 30, 1922 - 1922 (undated), 1922 (Box 7, Folder 19)
    - January 14, 1923 - March 14, 1923, 1923 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - March 15, 1923 - July 19, 1923, 1923 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - July 23, 1923 - October 17, 1923, 1923 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - October 22, 1923 - December 5, 1923, 1923 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - December 6, 1923 - January 22, 1924, 1923-1924 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - January 26, 1924 - May 15, 1924, 1924 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - May 20, 1924 - 1924 (undated), 1924 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - January 1, 1925 - September 29, 1925, 1925 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - October 1, 1925 - February 15, 1926, 1925-1926 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - March 1, 1926 - 1926 (undated), 1926 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - October 13, 1926 - January 12, 1927, 1926-1927 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - January 11, 1927 - June 13, 1927, 1927 (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - July 8, 1927 - January 21, 1928, 1927-1928 (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - January 10, 1928 - September 4, 1928, 1928 (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - September 7, 1928 - 1928 (undated), 1928 (Box 8, Folder 15)
    - January 2, 1929 - July 15, 1929, 1929 (Box 8, Folder 16)
    - July 23, 1929 - 1929 (undated), 1929 (Box 8, Folder 17)
    - January 5, 1930 - April 16, 1930, 1930 (Box 8, Folder 18)
    - April 29, 1930 - November 28, 1930, 1930 (Box 8, Folder 19)
    - November 29, 1930 - May 30, 1931, 1930-1931 (Box 8, Folder 20)
    - June 5, 1931 - October 18, 1931, 1931 (Box 8, Folder 21)
    - November 6, 1931 - July 26, 1932, 1931-1932 (Box 8, Folder 22)
    - August 20, 1932 - February 21, 1933, 1933 (Box 8, Folder 23)
    - March 6, 1933 - September 1, 1933, 1933 (Box 8, Folder 24)
    - September 5, 1933 - December 8, 1933, 1933 (Box 8, Folder 25)
    - December 9, 1933 - March 6, 1934, 1933-1934 (Box 8, Folder 26)
    - March 8, 1934 - August 23, 1934, 1934 (Box 8, Folder 27)
    - September 12, 1934 - March 5, 1935, 1934-1935 (Box 8, Folder 28)
    - March 6, 1935 - March 26, 1935, 1935 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - March 27, 1935 - May 3, 1935, 1935 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - May 6, 1935 - May 24, 1935, 1935 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - May 26, 1935 - June 13, 1935, 1935 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - June 17, 1935 - February 24, 1938, 1935-1938 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - March 5, 1938 - November 4, 1938, 1938 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - January 11, 1939 - 1940 (misc clippings), 1939-1940 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - 1938-1941 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - 1938-1942 (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - August 5, 1942 - December 16, 1942, 1942 (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - 1942 (undated) - May 10, 1943, 1942-1943 (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - May 23, 1943 - September 7, 1944, 1943-1944 (Box 9, Folder 12)
    - September 22, 1944 - June 16, 1945, 1944-1945 (Box 9, Folder 13)
    - December 29, 1945 - November 1947 (and undated), 1945-1947 (Box 9, Folder 14)
    - June 27, 1945 - June 8, 1948, 1945-1948 (Box 9, Folder 15)
    - October 8, 1947 - October 1948 (and undated), 1947-1948 (Box 9, Folder 16)
    - November 1, 1948 - December 29, 1949, 1948-1949 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - January 17, 1949 - December 1950, 1949-1950 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - September 17, 1948 - October 1948, 1948 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - November 22, 1948 - February 15, 1949, 1948-1949 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - February 27, 1949 - April 15, 1949, 1949 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - April 26, 1949 - September 10, 1950, 1949-1950 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - September 18, 1950 - February 10, 1951, 1950-1951 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - February 15, 1951 - March 25, 1951, 1951 (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - April 11, 1951 - August 22, 1951, 1951 (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - August 27, 1951 - June 30, 1952, 1951-1952 (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - May 22, 1952 - August 7, 1952, 1952 (Box 10, Folder 11)
    - August 28, 1952 - December 16, 1952, 1952 (Box 10, Folder 12)
    - December 25-1952 - June 30, 1953, 1952-1953 (Box 10, Folder 13)
    - October 5, 1953 - December 31, 1954, 1953-1954 (Box 10, Folder 14)
    - January 2, 1955 - July 29, 1955, 1955 (Box 10, Folder 15)
    - August 10, 1955 - September 30, 1955, 1955 (Box 10, Folder 16)
    - October 4, 1955 - December 6, 1955, 1955 (Box 10, Folder 17)
    - January 11, 1956 - March 10, 1956, 1956 (Box 10, Folder 18)
    - April 22, 1956 - March 1957, 1956-1957 (Box 10, Folder 19)
    - March 18, 1957 - January 23, 1958, 1957-1958 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - January 25, 1958 - March 23, 1959, 1958-1959 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - March 24, 1959 - September 3, 1959, 1959 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - January 21, 1960 - October 12, 1960, 1960 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - October 15, 1960 - February 10, 1961, 1960-1961 (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - February 11, 1961 - October 12, 1963, 1961-1963 (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - March 1963 - October 11, 1965, 1963-1965 (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - Elsa and the children, undated (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - Family, undated (Box 11, Folder 9-10)
    - Friends, undated (Box 11, Folder 11-12)
    - General, undated (Box 11, Folder 13)
    - Christmas cards sent, 1917-1939 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Christmas cards sent, 1940-1949 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Christmas cards sent, 1950-1957 (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - Christmas cards sent, 1957-1963 (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - Christmas cards received A-B, 1914-1963 (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - Christmas cards received - B, 1937-1964 (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - Christmas cards received - D, 1912-1962 (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - Christmas cards received - E and G, 1925-1963 (Box 12, Folder 8)
    - Christmas cards received - H, 1957-1963 (Box 12, Folder 9)
    - Christmas cards received - H, undated (Box 12, Folder 10)
    - Christmas cards received - K (S), 1924-1963 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Christmas cards received - K-L, 1932-1963 (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Christmas cards received - M and P, 1924-1963 (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Christmas cards received - R-S, 1942-1957 (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - Christmas cards received - S-T (Allen), 1943-1964 (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - Christmas cards received - U and W, 1941-1964 (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - Christmas cards received - V, 1913-1952 (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - Christmas cards received - W, undated (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Business Correspondence
    - 1913 (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - 1914 (Box 14, Folder 2-3)
    - 1915 (Box 14, Folder 4-5)
    - 1916 (Box 14, Folder 6-8)
    - 1919-1921 (Box 14, Folder 9)
    - 1922 (Box 14, Folder 10)
    - 1923 (Box 14, Folder 11)
    - 1924 (Box 14, Folder 12)
    - 1925 (Box 14, Folder 13-15)
    - 1926 (Box 14, Folder 16)
    - 1927 (Box 14, Folder 17)
    - 1928 (Box 14, Folder 18)
    - 1929 (Box 14, Folder 19-20)
    - 1930 (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - 1931 (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - 1932 (Box 15, Folder 3)
    - 1933 (Box 15, Folder 4)
    - 1934 (Box 15, Folder 5)
    - Bird Slide and film materials, 1942-1944 (Box 15, Folder 6)
    - Moving picture film materials, 1939-1942 (Box 15, Folder 7)
    - A, 1942-1945 (Box 15, Folder 8)
      Bird photograph slide business
    - B, 1942-1946 (Box 15, Folder 9)
    - C, 1941-1947 (Box 15, Folder 10-11)
    - D, 1942-1946 (Box 15, Folder 12)
    - E, 1943-1946 (Box 15, Folder 13)
    - F, 1943-1946 (Box 15, Folder 14)
    - G, 1943-1946 (Box 15, Folder 15)
    - H, 1942-1946 (Box 15, Folder 16)
    - J, 1946 (Box 15, Folder 17)
    - K, 1942-1946 (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - L, 1942-1946 (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - Mc, 1942-1946 (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - M, 1942-1946 (Box 16, Folder 4)
    - N, 1943-1946 (Box 16, Folder 5)
    - O, 1943-1946 (Box 16, Folder 6)
    - P, 1942-1946 (Box 16, Folder 7)
    - R, 1942-1946 (Box 16, Folder 8)
    - S, 1942-1946 (Box 16, Folder 9)
    - T, 1943-1947 (Box 16, Folder 10)
    - U, 1943-1945 (Box 16, Folder 11)
    - V, 1942-1946 (Box 16, Folder 12)
    - W, 1943-1946 (Box 16, Folder 13)
    - Y, 1943-1946 (Box 16, Folder 14)
    - A, 1946-1947 (Box 16, Folder 15)
    - B, 1946-1947 (Box 16, Folder 16)
    - C, 1946-1947 (Box 17, Folder 1)
    - D-F, 1947 (Box 17, Folder 2)
    - G, 1946-1947 (Box 17, Folder 3)
    - I-L, 1946-1947 (Box 17, Folder 4)
    - Mc-N, 1946-1948 (Box 17, Folder 5)
    - O-P, 1946-1947 (Box 17, Folder 6)
    - R, 1946-1947 (Box 17, Folder 7)
    - S-T, 1946-1947 (Box 17, Folder 8)
    - U-Z, 1946-1947 (Box 17, Folder 9)
    - List of slides ordered from Arthur Allen, 1948 (Box 17, Folder 10)
    - A, 1948 (Box 17, Folder 11)
    - B, 1948 (Box 17, Folder 12)
    - C-D, 1948 (Box 17, Folder 13)